test, test, test, test, test
>> good afternoon.
Welcome to the JANUARY 2025
meeting of the board of
supervisors.
>> thank you.
MR. PRESIDENT.
Supervisor chan
>> present
>> supervisor chen.
>> present.
>> supervisor dorsey.
>> engardio.
>> present sgrochl fileder.
>> present.
>> mahmood.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> present.
>> brierz melgar.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> present.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> supervisor walton.
>> all members are present.
>> thank you.
The san francisco board
acknowledges weer unseed home
land of the recommend ram.
The original inhabitants of the
san francisco peninsula.
As indigenous stewards and with
their traditions they have never
cd, lost nor forgotten their
responsibilities as the care
takers of this place.
As well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory.
As guests we recognize we
benefit from living and working
on their traditional home land.
We wish to acknowledge the
ancestors, elders and relatives
of the recommend ram community
and a if he wering their rights
as first peoples.
.
Join neil in me in reciting the
pledge.
>>[Pledge of allegiance].
On behalf of the board I want to
acknowledge the fantastic staff
at sfgovtv and today I want to
acknowledge colleena mendoza
they record the meetings and
make transcripts available for
the public online and we're
grateful to them.
MADAM Clerk are there
communications.
>> thank you the board welcomes
attendance in person in the
board's chamber room 250.
Or watch them on sfgov.Org
channel 26 or live stream at
sfgov.Org.
You MAY submit your public
comment by sending an e mail to
sfgov.Org or the U.S. Postal
service to the san francisco
board of supervisors.
1 DR. Carlton b. Goodlett place
room 244, san francisco, 94102.
To make an accomodation under
the ad a or request language
assistance, contact the clerk's
office 2 days in advance.
And MR. PRESIDENT.
Today the clerk's office is in
receipt of three ad a
accommodation requests.
The first one is a remote
caller.
The second is an in person
commenter who needs
interpretation services.
And the third person will be in
person they are an individual
with a disability.
Thank you.
MR. PRESIDENT.
Why thank you, in dam clerk.
We have those 3 ad a requests
for accomodation we will take
first commenter.
>> all right.
To the clerk staff.
Can we have the remote caller,
please?
The timer is two minutes
>> hello.
I'm ramonea, I live in a
[Inaudible] Next door to the
ship yard.
Gt c closed [Inaudible].
According to city charter 16
section 16.112, should have been
an opinion hearing with notice
prior to limiting service or
closing it.
We would like to ask this be put
on the agenda to have them.
And the department asked why
that did not happen in the first
place?
The more important thing is this
we have been told the sheriffs
will be here on FEBRUARY 14 to
someone will impound our rv's
there are 35 people in a high
state of panic that is the
reason I come before the board.
And sent a few e mails.
California vehicle code 22650b
states that any removal of a
vehicle is a seizure under the
fourth amendment of the
constitution of the united
states and section 13 article 1
of california constitution
should be reasonable and
preseizure hearing you will hear
others talk about the continuous
I have been plain in e mails to
the board.
I have been making grievances
and we don't want it to get
violent out here.
These are people's homes.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you to the caller and
staff.
We have someone who is here in
person.
Who would like interpretation
assist analysis.
We have two microfoes the
speaker can speak for two
minutes and then the interpreter
will interpret for the speaker.
I have been living there for
2-1/2 years a lot of
discrimination and the area.
I have not had access to sign
language for two years.
I have been requesting them.
One afternoon move to a
different area, but my car had
been towd and had no idea there
was no interpreter I was not
expecting my car to be gone.
And so I was overwhelmed and I
have been experiencing
discrimination.
I'm asking to extend the
deadline for 90 more days I need
more time to repair my rv.
I have been asking for repairs
and they have been delayed and
it is deteriorating.
And has not been repaired for
two years I need more timism
can't do it I can't do it by you
know the time dead line they are
given I need 90 more days,
please, to do that.
Thank you.
>> thank you for coming down
this afternoon.
And we have a third person in
person.
Welcome.
You wanted to use that and pull
the microphone down.
Welcome.
Hello.
I'm kelly hughes I live in an rv
at the bt c there for 30 months.
Because of the my wheel chair
I'm in the centers of an
investigation by hud the city
for the city's over the city's
lack of ad a compliance the
department of homelessness was
one who offered me relocation to
my family in texas.
I was second in line for repairs
that then stopped in -- to the
hud investigation.
I was skipped over by bayview
foundation.
Took a bus load of people to the
dmv I was not told and they also
got tires I didn't.
Then I year goes by there is
damage from rats.
Dfrj damages from employee who
republican in my bumper twice
and hit the front of my rv.
Also one of the urban employees
broke my door by too hard
example my windows fall koren
out.
Finely the department was forced
by hud to hire an ad a
consultant.
He got me an accomodation to get
repairs because of the city's
refusal to make it ad a
compliant.
This is an on going problem.
Everyone of their accommodations
requests are being ignored.
OCTOBER 7 we got approved
ramonea and I got it.
She was -- a witness to the
retelliation for being a witness
to the hud case.
My winds shield on one side all
my wiring is out
>> ma'am.
We can take the copy of that if
you like and mitt it in the
record for you.
Is that a copy we can keep or do
we need to make a copy of if t
you have a sentence sure sorry.
We are seth the time are for 2
minutes.
I will say then that thank you
for having me and we do need an
extension.
Nobody is housed all their
accommodations are denied I
don't know why.
but we do need more time you
know they started they finished
helpful repairs and stopped.
And like mou it is raining in my
rv they got half I wind shield
in.
Thank you.
Why would you like us to collect
this document and put it in the
record
record?
Sure.
That completes accommodations.
Thank you.
Let's go to the consent agenda
1-9.
>> on consent.
These are considered routine if
a member objects an item removed
and considered separately.
>> all right.
Does anyone wish to sever
anything from consent?
I don't see anybody.
Did can you call the roll.
>> items 1-9.
Engardio.
>> aye.
>> supervisor fielder.
Why supervisor mahmood.
>> aye.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> aye.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> aye.
>> supervisor walton.
>> supervisor chan.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chen.
>> and supervisor dorsey.
>> aye.
>> there are 11 aye's.
>> without objection they are
finally passed.
>> let's go to new busy items 10
and 11.
Together.
>> 10 and 11 ordinances pertain
to certificates of participation
for the port of san francisco.
Item 10 an ordinance authorizes
the execution and delivery of
refunding cop's that courteouses
of participation.
And evidencing and representing
and aggregate amount of 25
million.
To prepay previous other cop's
finance the design and
construction reconstruction,
expansion, improvement
equipping, renewal.
Of capitol improve ams to
properties to approve the form
of various authorizing
documents.
Such as the supplement to the
trust.
The project lease.
Relate to the lease and the
lease back of a portion of the
james herman cruise terminal at
pier 27.
The notify of sale and dprekt
the notice of intention to sell.
And to approve formless.
Item 11 appropriates 28.Throw
million and I will skip to --
also 483,000 of series 2013b and
1.995 million of 23c.
Prior debt service reserve
proceeds.
And the appropriate 900,000
series 2033b prokt funds to the
port commission for 6.4 million
to the refunding certificates of
participation.
Series 2025-r1 and 22 million to
redundzing certificates of
anticipation series 25r-2 and
place them on controller's
reserve pending the sale of the
reach proceed in fiscal year
2024-25.
>> thank you.
I think we can take same house
same call they are passod first
reading.
>> can you call 12.
>> item 12 amends the business
and tax code to exempt from
commercial vacancy tax beginning
on JANUARY first, 25.
Any taxable commercial space
located in either a named
neighborhood commercial or
transit district a city
infrastructure or construction
project has a construction
duration of more than 180 days
in a calendar year and from
JANUARY of 22 through DECEMBER
of 24 any taxable commercial
space located in the
neighborhood commercial district
orrin are taraval street.
Members with article 29 section
2909 of the business and tax
regulation code passage of this
ordinance is vote of 8 votes of
the board.
>> and I believe we can take
this same house same call
without objection it is passod
first reading.
>> call 13
>> item 13 an ordinance to amend
the administrative code for the
core initiatives to strengthen
city's sponse to homelessness
and related crisis.
>> supervisor chan.
>> thank you.
PRESIDENT Mandelman.
And colleague this is item come
from the budget committee.
Um votes to support the item but
not without amendments there are
amendments that I think many of
you have familiar with.
And -- I just want it thank the
mayor and his team working
clantive with the legislative
branch on a compromise
legislation.
It irrelevant does give the
executive branch ways to
implement their vision.
Without waiving all oversight
authority from the legislative
branch.
With that said after the
approval there were a few more
technical details that needed to
be resolved including edits and
language.
I want to thank supervisor
fielder for doing the heard work
to propose additional amendments
to really help narrow the scope
of the behest waiver. And
adding moreover sight to this
legislation.
These amendments were already
mailed to you thanks to mayor's
office, MR. Adam -- thank you.
And so it should be in your
inbox, colleagues.
But to make sure that.
We go through this for the
public.
Is had we will see on page 1 to
clarify in the long title we
show this is accept and extend
for the donation to
nongovernmental sources for the
core initiative can be up to 10
million dollars.
Limning a 10 million dollars
this is page one line 15.
On page 8, line 4, we are
showing that original low we say
the date of introduction.
We want to clarify that the date
of legislation introduced but
the clerk of the board limp is a
technical -- requirements
between the tuesday introduction
and friday publish with the file
number and title.
And then we are also seeing line
24 -- that's a clarifying the 45
day shot clock and line 24 and
25 on page 14, is to go through
the scope of the narrow down
those who can receive the waiver
for the behest waiver.
I will turn to supervisor jackie
fielder to speak on details.
Over all, I wanted to say,
again, you know this has
narrowed down to a deadline of
JANUARY 8, 2026.
This gives all of us a chance to
see that the mayor's plan and
vision will be and how we
deliver on temperature but this
is going to come become to us
and we as a body can evaluate
the plan and tweak it and to
give feedback to the plan dp &
continue oversight to what we
ought to do for the executive
branch to deliver for san france
and with that I thank you.
>> thank you supervisor chan.
I thank you and the budget
mittee for your work and engage
am.
And supervisor fieldser?
>> they were I want to thank
chair chan for her amendments.
And mayor lurie for working with
my team to provide transparency
will narrow the scope and and
positions this are subject to
the behested payments waiver and
claire include expediting hiring
of behavioral health
professionals.
Today ooem vote nothing support
of mayor lurie's emergency
ordinance.
In the tackling the fentanyl and
over dose crisis.
And with my vote I want to be
clear that this ordinance is an
unprecedentsed transfer of
power.
And a significant transfer of
responsibility to mayor lurie to
transform street conscience the
next year.
with my vote today I'm putting a
great deal of faith in mayor
lurie's administration to
utilize the extraordinary 4s
carry out the will of the voters
and provide housing, shelter and
treatment to our most vulnerable
and to do so, without repeating
the corrupt practices that have
tainted the public's trust in
city government for years.
I await comprehensive details
about the mayor's plans to
stands up and staff the hundreds
of treatment beds that the city
still needs to make progress on
this issue.
As the mayor develops plans I
will encourage the
administration to look at 4
pillar's model a strategy
address being drug use, mentel
ill expense homelessness.
Sings the crack down and mass
arrestos drug users last year an
increase in shift of people from
the tenderloin and soma to the
mission.
And that is not a strategy.
Other countries have been
successful.
Switzerland and portugal
overwhelmed with over dose when
is they devise the strategies on
enforcement and investments in
treatment and street out reach
and health care coverage and
recognize addiction as a
disease, they made remarkable
gains by decreasing opioid
deaths by 64% and heroin
addiction by 75%.
We need to implement a similar
plan locally.
Utilizing the bl areport to
impelement the 4 pillar strategy
requested by preston and the
board of supervisors.
Our work here after passing this
is not done.
the mayor as an opportunity now
to convene experts and policy
makers across the political
spectrum to make sure we are
alined in look step under one
strategy.
I will do my part to continue to
work in good faith to ensure the
success of this ordinance is not
just for one mayor or for one
district.
I will ask that I can those
without objection.
I think
>> MR. PRESIDENT walton is on
the roster.
We will call after the ma'am and
before we vote on the amended
legislation.
>> so we take the amendments
without objection.
>> and then I will call on
supervisor walton.
>> thank you.
PRESIDENT Mandelman.
During the covid pandemic we
granted emergency powers with
the presence of a plan.
Now we have before us
legislation that among other
things requests waiving approval
processes for contracking,
waiving our behested payment
policies all without knowing
what will be done.
We don't have a plan in front of
us that details what the mayor's
team plans to do with these
emergency powers.
This is probably the most vivid
example of putting the cart
before the hours horse I have
seen in my years in office
supporting this legislation as
is extremely prein tour.
Not only is there the absence of
a plan there is also the acsense
of knowing how much this will
cost the city according to the
bla and the fiscal impact of the
proposed ordinance is difficult
to estimate.
Since the universe of contracts
this will or men awarded is not
yet known.
And in addition the aim of funds
raising that could off set now
cost system unknown.
So we are talking about the
possibility of a blank check.
And at least 100 million dollars
and the mayor can change without
process.
Our checks and balance system of
gentleman was put in place so
the people have representation
on all sides.
So that we don't have a
dictatorship in san francisco
gentleman.
I will continue to support
working together on a plan that
determines what laws we need to
change for its success if and
when it is presented and
supported by this body.
I'm not sure when we started
preemping emergency powerhouse.
I have been told this is I plan
to get 1500 beds.
Where, how?
I want it support strajs and
plan this is get us somewhere.
And while I agree it is an
unprecedented time, this is why
we need an unpresidented plan to
address the fentanyl crisis and
mental health crisis in the
city.
I have not seen a plan I cannot
vote, yes in the absense of I
plan.
Strategy or something besides
strong words.
Thank you, MR. PRESIDENT.
>> thank you supervisor walton.
I don't see anyone else on the
roster call the roll on the
ordinance as amended
>> item supervisor mahmood is on
the roster
>> I wanted before
voting -- mented vote in support,
I mentioned left time I commend
the mayor's intentionality.
To cut through the red tape to
allow government action on an
issue that requires urgency.
It hen over due for our
residents in the tenderloin.
I do want to thank my colleagues
and supervisor chan and the
budget and finance for passing
item.
And for my colleague who is
cosponsored this is heeding the
call to take our community safer
but showing and the board can
work together for the good of
our residence denials.
At the core of what this does is
helps the city get out of its
way to deliver life saving
resources to the neighbor who
need it most.
Our departments will expand
service and provide critical
resource the tool kits to get
the job done.
A crisis gone on for too long
this is the first step to
providing the tools we need to
improve safety and bring change
to our communities and given to
restore hope that's why I will
vote, yes.
>> thank you.
With that, MADAM Clerk.
Can you call the roll on the
ordinance.
>> item 13 as amended
supervisor engardio.
>> aye.
Why supervisor fielder.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> aye.
Supervisor mandelman.
>> supervisor melgar.
>> aye.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> aye.
>> supervisor walton.
>> no.
>> supervisor chan.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chen.
>> supervisor dorsey.
>> aye.
There are 10 aye's and one no
with supervisor walton voting,
no
>> thank you, call the next
item.
>> item 14.
This is resolution to approve
the third ma'am with community
services and department of
homelessness.
For short two medium rapid
rehousing grant term extended 29
months through JUNE 30 of 20 and
increase the agreement amount
for a new total of 21.5 million.
Can you cal the rolfe this?
>> item 14.
Supervisor engardio.
>> aye.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> aye.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> supervisor melgar.
Why aye.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> aye.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> supervisor walon.
>> aye.
>> supervisor chan.
>> supervisor chen.
>> aye.
>> supervisor dorsey.
>> there are 11 aye's.
>> thank you, I guess we have
half a machine left call 15-18
together.
>> 15-184 resolutions approve
agreements of department, youth
and families.
15, provides retroactive
approval with dcyf and community
youth center for 4 programs
through JUNE 30 of 29.
13.Sen million.
16, retroactive approval for an
agreement with the commune youth
center of san finish for 4
programs.
5 year term through JUNE 30 are
29 for 11.7 million.
17, approval for an agreement --
two programs 5 year term through
JUNE 302029 and 12.9 million.
Item 18.
Retroactive approval for an
agreement with the neighborhood
center for 4 programs a 5 year
term and 10.Throw million.
>> supervisor sauter.
>> sauter.
>> thank you.
>> colleagues I wish to make a
disclosure for 18 I served the
executive director of san
francisco neighborhood centers
together the grantee for the
item richmond district is the
sponsor of my former employer.
I no longer are financial rep
with my former empployer and
after I have been advised I
don't have a conflict of
interest and don't need to
recuse myself I wanted share
this.
Thank you.
>> thank you supervisor
sauter.
We can take these items same
house same call without
objection.
these are adopted.
And -- can you take us to the
2:30 special order.
>> recognition of commendations
from service to the city and
count I of san francisco.
>> all right.
We will begin today with
district 4 supervisor joel
engardio.
>> colleagues.
The girl's flag football team at
lincoln high school made history
wing the first san francisco
triple asection energy football
championship.
All right!
And -- not only that.
There is more.
This historic win was
memorialize in the an article in
sports illustrated!
Yes!
So -- be sure to google and read
the article it includes photos
and video of the game.
Congratulations to the team they
have shown dedication and team
work and perseverance all of
this was under the guidance of
coach williams and coach
branner.
Congratulations to the entire
lincoln high school community.
Go mustangs!
[Applause] I like to invite the
coach for a few word busy this
rable team
>> thank you.
>> first I want to thank GOD and
lincoln.
Thank these young ladies for
ltd.Ing mow coach them.
My assistant coaches.
>> thank GOD for everything.
These ladies are wonderful.
And I want it thank lincoln high
school for giving me the
opportunity to coach these young
ladies.
i got a speech I want to say.
For you guys.
Back in what day?
Turkey day.
Was historical moment the first
time girls have ever
participated in a turkey day
bowl.
We were the first team to ever
win temperature you know give
yourself a hand for that.
[Applause]
>> this is in the just a win on
the score board a testament to
everything we work for the
sweat.
Hard work and practices we put
in.
Every day, you show the world
when it means to play with a
passion.
To never give up and support one
another through every challenge.
You guys are broken barriers
special set new standards this
is prove can you do anything
possible.
Let's care this to next we're
this is only the beginning of
something bigger.
>> you know, we made history.
It is like, I want you to know
you made history.
Congratulations, again.
[Applause].
>> -- go mustangs!
[Laughter] [Applause] District
10 supervisor walton.
Thank you.
Today kickoff our black history
celebration, we want to start
off by proudly recognizing joyce
armstrong!
[Applause] Recognizing -- joyce
armstrong for her unwaivering
dedication and tireless service
to d 10 in potrero hill but san
francisco as a whole.
Over 3 decades.
MRS. Armstrong a champion for
youth, economic justice and
equal rights.
Shaping lives through her
leadership at the potrero
neighborhood house.
San francisco housing authority
and numerous advocacy
organizations.
For mendz oborring young people
of.
.
And gang prevention programs and
serving for public housing
residents, she continuous low
uplifted and empowered those
most in need.
Her legacy.
Service and activism has left a
mark on our city.
Ensure community thrive and
residence den vs a voice in
their future.
We commend joyce for her
lifelong commitment to justice
and equity and he honor her as a
beacon of leadership and recell
yens in our community.
As a black history among honoree
we commend her for being a trail
blazer for justice and
empowerment.
We honor her as pillar of
strength in our community and
black excellence in san
francisco!
Thank you.
Commissioners.
Supervisors.
I am so thankful to be honored
by the city and county of san
francisco again.
And especially by supervisor
walton who grew up me at the
neighborhood house we are so
proud of him.
My son I'm the mother of 3.
My oldest son was murder in the
2021.
I still have my son shawn, my
daughter who is trying to get
her I'm mother of 3 the grand
mother of scomplen great grand
mother of 5!
>> I have numerous people this
one of the kids this grew up
with mow at the neighboring
house's mother.
This is one of the grew up with
me -- threat evened run, way if
her mother did not get her cow
by boots for the talent show.
I was in trouble with all the
parents.
This since she was 3.
Sheryl.
My niece and says I love this
lady nowhere in the world I was
coming out in this rain.
I just am so proud I was able to
help pioneer the people of the
potrero public housing and
citywide.
In a naeshg house that was open
and giving and did so much by
the honorable maxwell.
Many you have MAY not than is
sophie's mother.
She opened the door from the
mayor's I other than from jordan
to moscone
I we were in this city
hall all the time learning and
growing.
Over 50 years of work I wanted
thank you all and let's do
something good for this city.
We don't need to go back.
It is great.
If people move out the way.
I tell people do what I say and
everything will be okay.
[Applause] [Applause] All right.
District 2 supervisor steven
sherrill.
Colleagues.
Today we recognize brian's
incredible career in his
retirement after decades of
service to san francisco.
[Applause].
and turned around so I can see
you.
Brian, thank you.
As director of community
development office of house and
community development brian
strength korened communities.
Affordable how doing and uplift
residents for 20 years.
Under his leadership ocd
directed fund to hundreds of
community based organizations
ensuring resources reach the
most in need.
But his commitment to service
stands over 20 years here in
public service.
But also in nonprofit
leadership.
Civil rights and teaching.
Because teaching in hong kong
and indz why was not enough he
moved to san francisco and
serviced director of throw major
nonprofits in the city.
Lyric.
Stan fran lbgtq+ community
center and chinese for, firmtive
action.
That was not enough.
He work the as a representative
at the san fan human right's
commission and ordinances and
advancing historically
marginalized communities.
That was not enough.
Devoted himself to housing.
Beyond professional achievements
he is known for kindness.
Patience and deep commitment to
uplifting others.
He is quote, this is a quote
from a real human.
Nicest empathetic person I have
issue met.
He urn everearned the trust of
city officials.
Brings people together to create
meaningful change.
He will be missed by colleagues
but more important low by his
favorite jap need bento box
restaurant.
Brian's leadership shaped the
future of this city of behalf of
the board we thank you for your
service and wish you the best in
your well earned retirement.
Brian, thank you.
If I might just add, because you
are still my constituent.
Couple decades ago when I was
first starting to get involved
in san francisco civic and
political life I knew of brian
chu I think before he knew of he
I thought he was a really big
deal.
I have seen that you
accomplished and a pleasure to
work with you for you.
With you, both.
The last 6 and a half yearis
still think you are a big deal I
think of you as a friends and
you deserve this retirement.
Thank you for all you have done
for us.
And you are not you don't get to
talk yet supervisor chan also
wants to say something.
Gi want to thank you PRESIDENT
Machine man.
I realliment it say thank you
for all the work you have done.
We few year ago couple of years
ago we allocated collectively on
the board of supervisors and
mayor breed together have
allocated 30 million dollars to
the ap I fund.
And it was a difficult thing to
do buzz we have never done it
before.
It make sure a way to support ap
I organizations.
That00 organizations that serve
the ap I community can stay in
san francisco to continue to
serve and not to have to face
eviction as nonprofits.
But because never done before
brian was in a position to come
away to get this money out the
door and fair and equal
integrity process.
And it was not easy and I'm
grateful for your work.
I than one example for many
things that you have done not
just in the city government
umbrella but your nonprofit work
before then.
For that you will be missed and
for who is mixed up in your shoe
vs big shoes to fill and thank
you for your leadership and
service to our community.
Thank you.
[Applause] Thank you.
Supervisor chan.
And now brian you MAY speak.
[Laughter].
Thank you, supervisors.
For this honor I feel
privilegeed have been able to
serve this city for 20 years.
And I will say that prebl the
greatest honor for me is to be
able to have this the
opportunity to get to know the
residents of communities and the
diversity of know front.
I think it it is -- working for
the city is a mrij it all
respects.
And I will say that --
especially now as we face so
many threats from the outside.
The ability to be in san pran
and in a place that recognizes
the importance and celebrates
all the various identities and
needs of all the communities --
many people in the country and
cross the world don't have now.
And -- so -- I don't want to
take that for granted.
I wanted thank the amazing team
at mohcd.
you know my work is really just
being able to support the
fabulous leadership and staff
with whom I worked for the past
20 years.
And -- while I -- I will not
MISS Having to come to this
chamber and make presentations.
-- I will MISS The wonderful
friend this is I made here.
And their commitment to makeing
city a better place.
Thank you again.
For all that you have done for
the city and thank all of my
family -- at mayor's office.
Thank you.
Thank you again.
I appreciate it.
All right and lastly but not
leastly in the spirit of
honoring big deal public sector
leaders.
I'd like to invite colfax.
[Applause] It is my honor to
present accomodation to grant
nash colfax who is retiring
FEBRUARY sen after leading the
public health for 6 years.
And man, what a 6 year its has
been.
Graduate of harvard complete in
the internal medicine.
Began at sfpdh in 1983 at san
francisco general.
In 1998 after completing
training joined the aid office
and focused on researching h I v
prevention.
Brought an approach addressing
gap in care and prevention.
Joined obama administration.
Grant was the administration's
advisor on policy and
coordinates to implement the
aids strategy.
He lead social services and
behavioral health on health
equity in marin in FEBRUARY of
2019 return today public health
as director and dph is our
largest department with a
throw.2 billion dollars budget.
And more than 8,000 employees.
As director initiate the
programs to support the
treatment and recovery manage
and behavioral healing workers
in supportive housing and
pharmacies delivered to those
maintaining recovery.
Dp heart attack opened the
martinez clinic to provide
urgent care for unhoused
individual for substance
abecause or mental health.
Telea health for medication
treatment and lobbies the state
and congress to reform methadone
miles an hour accessible.
Lead us through the pandemic
with highest vaccination rate in
upon country.
San francisco the first city to
establish testing for essential
wars.
After years of staffing
shortages and 85% of equity plan
and goals.
When laguna honda lost
certification worked with
regulators to save hospital and
reinstate certification.
And even serving as director he
treated patients living with
aids at san francisco's
general's ward 86.
What feels like a full circle
dph, nounsed new infection rates
72% to the lowest levels ever.
Grant's research and work on hiv
prevention are literally bearing
fruit now for our community.
>> public health work is ground
in the science, data and facts
delivered through compassion and
caring for others.
Thank you for your amazing and
incredible service to this city.
We wish you well and we are
grateful.
Now you can take it away.
Thank you I appreciate your kind
words and the support of this
amazing policy, body and I have,
lot of things to talk about but
you mentioned those.
So.
Perhaps the first time in 6
years I'm speechless.
Usually I have something to say.
I just you know -- I really want
to express my gratitude and
honor I had to serve as head of
the department and I want to
take a moment to revisit the
fact that you know what lead mow
to san francisco -- was the fact
that -- when I was young my
family received care at the
general.
We did not have insurance it was
a different time.
And the compassion that I saw
there was instrumental in me
think burglar a career in
medicine and public health.
Returning years later as a
medical student from the east
coast to 5 awas the hiv ward in
san francisco general.
And seeing the connection of
true community centered care.
People talk about that now.
Nobody was talking about it then
except in san francisco and
seeing what the community and bh
science could do together.
Was so inspiring.
It lead me to ucsf to train.
I knew that it was where I
wanted to be.
I think that culture continues
in san francisco and continues
and in the staechl and
conscience in dph.
Dph saves lives and improves
lives all the while trying to
improve health in san francisco.
You withinllow the data finance
and facts about what dph does.
An honor to see the board and
mayor's support massive big
infrastructure changes loyal
manage this sounds bonjour
rattic an trannic medical
record.
Not secy when you see what it
does on the ground and how you
help pating and get them care
effectively it makes all the
difference.
Our collaboration with other
city institutions including ucsf
a special rep with them where we
can turn academic
>> to programs on the ground.
Hospital council and the san
francisco healing plan.
So important in delivery of
care.
I want to acknowledge and
appreciate the support of the
health commission through the
times.
And appreciate all you have our
mayors and -- for their vision
and support of the department.
Which makes the w pobl.
We recruited talityents at the
department.
The vacancy going down.
We got to zero, which is
unprecedented.
I want to take a moment to
celebrate the fact that people
don't say it when they leave
they do great things.
We have apatrol the city and
outside of the city that MR.
Greg wagner our first chief
operating officer gone on as
controller.
We have doctor argone our health
director to become the state
health director for california.
She is not here but doctor
bennett the director of health
equity.
Was recruit exclude I'm proud
she is the director of health at
in wish washington, D.C.
Amazing people come from dph.
It is because dph is committed
and collaborative.
Community focused, account
believe and data drivenism know
that dph will condition to
provide the best care.
Using approaches that work.
And dp heart attack will keep
the people we serve front in
center of when we do no matter
what.
Thank you temperature hen an
honor to serve.
[Applause]
>> ready.
Okay.
I think we left off at 14 we are
at 15.
Regular agenda?
We are at item 19.
>> 19.
You are correct.
>> I'm wrong.
Thank you.
>> yea.
Call 19
>> thank you MR. PRESIDENT.
A resolution to retroactively
authorize the public defender's
office accept 250 thousand
grant.
To fund the san frap public
defender clean slate unit to
meet demand for services JULY of
24 through JUNE of 25.
Same house same call.
Without objection.
This is adopted.
MADAM Clerk.
Call item 20.
>> this is a resolution to
retroactively approve and
authorize the director of
property on behalf of the san
francisco police department.
To execute a left lanes of a
portion of the real property at
1-199 forest road building 278
with U.S. Department of home
land security U.S. Coast guard.
Federal government for 5 year
term and base of zero.
Same house same call.
Without objection.
It adopted.
>> call item 21.
>> a resolution to
retroactively authorize and
approve the lease of 3,000
square feet of office space
located at 745 franklin with
state of california.
Am development department for
human services agency jobs now
program.
To through DECEMBER of 29 and
base rent 105,000.
>> same house same call without
objection it is adopted.
Call item 22.
>> 22, resolution approve and
authorize an ma'am to the lease
of approximately 11,000 square
feet of real property at sen 29
filbert with william piedmont
land lord to extend the term by
5 years for a term of DECEMBER
of 2018 lieu JANUARY 29 for base
rent of 4,000.
Why same house same call.
>> call item 23.
>> 23, resolution to
retroactively authorize major's
office of housing and commune
development accept a gift of
consulting services valued throw
45,000 from coreo northern
california.
.
Through upon JANUARY 31, 2027.
>> same house same call,
without objection, adopted.
Call item 24.
>> item 24, ordinance to amend
the planning code to allow
assessors parcel block 39-12
known as 99 rhode island street
to exceed the coupe welltive use
size requirements in production
distribution and repair
distinguishing condesign.
D 2 affirm ceqa and present
findings.
>> same house same call without
objection adopted.
>> MADAM Clerk call item 25.
>>
>> resolution to adopt the
castro lesbian bisexual
transgender queer district
cultural house and economic
sustainability strategy report.
Same house same call it is
adopted.
Call items 26 and upon 20
together
>> why are two resolutions
determine that the person to
person premise to premise
transfer type 21 beer, wine and
spirits liquor license will
serve the convenience necessity
of the city.
26 is for bar and llcdba bit and
bottle 1225 fell street and 27
city choice market db acity
choice market at 3 where are 1,
fifth the california department
of alcoholic beverage control
impose a condition on each
license.
Why same house same call without
objection.
Adopted.
>> call item 28.
>> 28, this is an ordinance to
exempt mid town park apartments
1415 scott street if
requirements in code chapter 6.
Requiring compliance with the
prevailing wage of coat section
23.61 and affirm the ceqa
determination
>> same house same call this is
passed on first reading.
>> and MADAM Clerk go to
committee reports.
>> item 29 is will considered
by land use committee at a
meeting on monday FEBRUARY
thishd and recommended an a
committee report.
29 is resolution to add the
street name on around are son
avenue between third and
griftive leading to the site
known at candlestick park
recognition of kingston to
america his affect on the
community.
Same house same call without
objection.
Adopted.
>> go to roll call.
>> supervisor engardio you are
first up?
Submit.
>> supervisor fielder.
>> today colleagues I would
like to introduce a resolution.
Rescue niedzing FEBRUARY of 25
as teen dating violence
awareness and prevention month.
It is important for us to reckon
with the fact that near low 1 in
throw teens experienced dating
violence during high school.
More most these experience other
first, introduction to reps with
others.
Research shows and we know these
issues can have long-term
impacts on one sense of self
worth.
Outlook and influence further
out come.
When dating violence and teen
relationships go unchecks,
unheard and unseen we risk the
cycles of abuse by perpetrators
and complainsancey toward
abusive actions continue to
adult hood.
The commission here today passed
a resolution part of their
commitment to preventing and
educating young people about
teen dating vinyls itchment to
thank our sdrkt 9 kouth
commissioner sky are dane and
gaby, and [Inaudible] Who have
shown leadership in bringing to
the board of supervisors.
Want to give a shout out to the
asian women shelter and black
women revolt to help teens
navigate and prevent unhealthy
reps.
Thank you it my intern who took
the lead in my office to pull
this together and thifrng my
clothes on the board of brierzs
for your early cosponsorship.
>> thank you.
Supervisor fielder.
Supervisor mahmood.
Submit
>> thank you.
>> supervisor mandelman.
>> all right.
I have a piece of legislation
and two in memoriams.
I am introducing ordinance to
establish the castro upper maker
entertainment zone covid-19 for
san francisco and cities to get
creative allowing more
commercial activity.
Out doors.
At the time moving outside was a
necessity.
But also people liked it.
Post pandemic local businesses
have in the recovered some
lessons learned from that period
are helping to inform our
economic recovery strategies.
Thanks to state level and sb76
and sb916 establishment of an
entertainment zone allows to
sell to go drink for people to
enjoy out doors and in the
streets during street closure
events the city established the
entertainment zones for front
street and today the board
approved an ordinance stake a
zone for cole valley with rich
queer night life the castro
seems like a fit for an
entertainment zone.
The fair and established castro
night markets are example of
event this is benefit from
establish am of an ez and
benefit local bars and
restaurants.
We anticipate there will be
other ways to put this to work
for the truants and small
businesses I want to thank lots
of people for help with this.
[Reading of names]
>> all right.
Then.
I also have two in memories.
I'm asking we adjourn the meet
nothing memory of richard
bowlingbrook died DECEMBER 28 at
the age of 74.
Grew up in england in 73
graduated from london university
studied geography.
Achieved success as an artist.
In 1976, rich order traveled ind
why lived for 5 years and
experienced defined his artistic
exploration.
After period in amsterdam,
oregon and phoenix he came to
san francisco in 86 and found a
culture that will be his forever
home.
A castro resident for 32 years
and freak wented the embarrass
especially the eagle.
Where he met his husband.
Steve gains in 1991.
His art work focussed on water
paintings with flowers this
benefitted work was created
during the aids epidemic when
richard questioned his own
existence.
He explained celebrating flowers
with acknowledge am rew hopeed
better sunday life itself and
work shift todd abstract style
and drew inspiration from text
urs of things around hem.
Later works muralos shot
welstreet and commission in
google's office.
He served the pedestrian of the
art of skill of san francisco
and board member.
In san francisco leather
community they were the family.
A group of 5 gay men now down to
4 we extend condolences.
Rest in peace and power miyour
memory be a blessing.
Also we adjourn today's meet
nothing memory of loved lifelong
castro resident al even berit.
He was ray dear man.
Passed away on JANUARY 7 at age
of 92.
Born in the castro he started as
a newspaper delivery driver.
We is make progress out look.
Like every major city around the
world we can make way per
development this promotes
righters.
Dinner or dry cleaning on your
way to catch muni and, luing the
agency to derive income this is
I win/win situation for housing,
transportation and our recovery.
This resolution calls for
network of a process.
To oyst which cites are
feasible, welcomed by neighbored
and beneficial to the stay stay
with a priority being the
financial well being of the
agency.
Arc seszable, affordable, safe
and reliable transportation
system is crucial for all our
other goals.
Makes access to education
possible workforce accessible
can special climate okay goals
sustainable.
Crucial we begin the
conversation to sustain our
system.
I want to thank my colleagues
supervisor sauter, engardio and
dorsey for early
coexperienceship of this
legislation.
Thank you.
The rest you submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor melgar.
>> supervisor sauter
>> commit
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> colleagues I want to thank
supervisor feeler near take the
lead on bringing where it is on
teen dating violence temperature
important this we never forget
the role we play with shining a
light on issues that are kept in
the dark.
Every survivor knows.
Supervisor speak directly in the
mic.
>> yes.
Why there we go.
I want to supervisor fielder,
thank you.
And want tos express gratitude
for my predecessor furthering w
in sacramento.
She introduced a concurred
resolution to proclaim month of
FEBRUARY teen dating violence
prevention month.
And I want to thank our san
francisco youth commission for
you ensure needs of young people
are heard in the halls it is
important work and resolutions
like this remind us why.
Today I'm intruzing a resolution
in support of bill 3 therein the
human tracking act authored by
member catherine stefani
spending 19 million dollars on
contracts the state of
california has in the updated
the contracting prosecute cure
am policies forced labor or
child labor since 2007.
Tell, line state luwith the
standards in 2016.
Adopting detailed guidance how
companies engage with supply
chains if they want to do
business with california human
trafficking calical is the
largest cites of human traffic
nothing the united states for
research by our own attorney
general.
Our state will leverage the
strengths to incent sunrise
companies to use human practice
and mow taxpayer money
criminalityed forced labor.
San francisco must stand
residencellow in xhugz to humane
practice and protection for all
in our state's policies.
The rest I submit.
>> thank you.
Supervisor walton.
>> submit.
Zo thank you.
Supervisor chan.
>> submit.
>> supervisor chen.
>> thank you.
Supervisor dorsey.
Clothes public safety staffing
the last few years merged a top
prior in our city for voters for
those of us on this board who
hear from our voters.
And also for mayor lurie.
Today I'm call figurar hearing
before neighborhood services
committee on staffing in the san
francisco district attorney's
office.
A public safety leadership in
our city this is often left out
of conversations that focus on
police, sheriffs 911e e ms and
others.
of interest to me and no small
number of voters ensuring we
impelement prop 36 passed with
70% of the vote and won here
citywide including wing every
district.
Prospect 36 holds twofold
promise not just to hold oshg
fenldzers accountable but also
to make use of treatment fell
niece I believe can make
criminal justice innerventions
for public drug use in life
saving interventions to do this
we need a staffed da's office.
I'm asking the office to report
on hat office needs to scale up
to match when we hope will be
scaled up and other agencies.
What resources will be necessary
to ensure that voters will is
reflected in a probable 36.
And obstacles policy makers
aware of in city hall to enable
us to help the da.
The rest I submit
>>
>> PRESIDENT.
This concludes introduction of
new business.
>> go to public comment.
>> the public are welcome to
lineup on the right hand side of
chamber you are able to speak to
general matters not on the
agenda but in the board's
jurisdiction.
Other agenda content reported
out by a mittee we are setting
the time are for two minutes.
I want to have a better
understanding if we bring a
question or.
I'm starting your time.
Skip this.
>> so.
D2 the conversation out there in
the hull way.
How you are justice for all.
Get you a lawyer.
my we have got on cam are me
being attacked by law
enforcement in california
[Inaudible] And impersonating
officers from another state.
[Inaudible].
I had to pay it back.
I was stabbed 9 times and member
got, way.
[Inaudible].
Me getting rest in the your
city.
Make no mistake I got I lawyer
here.
Expose that is going on here you
think I'm a nobody.
I'm a child of GOD.
Understanding stanninging up on
federal bureau investigation
property [Inaudible] Naked we
got on camera.
I can't do nothing for you.
You are not going to get
justice.
Put your arm behind my back to
sign a citation that was false.
Ladies and gentlemen, MR. Mayor,
I got a lawyer and got your
corruptions.
You should have lost.
[Inaudible].
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker, please.
Welcome.
>> good afternoon board of
supervisors.
I'm one of the ordinance of the
33 trailers in the r very close
center.
That will be displaceod 14th of
FEBRUARY.
I'm anim guarantee and live in
terror I'm terrified of what the
trump is going to do.
And -- my trailer that I --
moved to the location and there
for 4 year is broken.
It is infested with the ras and
have done nothing to control the
infestation.
We are discrape nayed against
and -- some of us are workers
and trying to relocate us to
rooms that are only 4 by 4 and I
don't have enough space for moiz
and throw cats ooem an addict in
recovery and want to put in the
tenderloin for me would mean I
will relapse in drug abuse.
I'm asking you for help.
To please, reach in your heart
to and have mercy for me I'm 50
years old I don't know when I do
if I koren up in the streets
again.
Thank you.
>> thank you for the
interpretation.
Next speaker.
>> good afternoon.
Good to see you angela.
Doing a great job I misyou I'm
barry toronto activist among
taxi workers.
I want to welcome the 5 new
supervisors most of you elected
one appointed I hope we get to
meet with you to talk about the
medallion situation and hat mt a
has done to hurt the industry
and our ability to serve our
passengers.
Who don't want to get gauged by
ewe uber and lyft.
Would like to urge you to ask
our state legislators to
regulate the autonomous
vehicles.
We don't need a thousand of them
on the streets.
They are safe for passengers but
not for the other vehicles on
the road those who drive for I
living or deliveries they
blocked streets and taxi stands
and well should be I way for
local entities sb915 was turned
down by lori wilson.
MAY be we can help bring it
become in I different form so
can you can regulate it.
I hope we can meet with the new
supervisors and explain what --
what can you do to help us.
With in religion to the mt a and
would being able to have
relationship with the cpu c and
with the state.
In terms of allowing municipal
tow work better.
Because again, we need to have a
public transit system.
Tell not work if people double
park and block roadways where
muni needs to go through
smoothly.
And because we are in a
community part of transit first
policy.
As taxi drivers and workers.
And you know we are part of taxi
program.
Serve disabled people in wheel
chairs that mode to get to
appointments and the program is
very successful.
So I want to thank you for your
time and happy lunar new year.
Exciting month
>> great to see you, be well.
>> next speaker, please.
Good afternoon.
I want to mention left week so,
[Inaudible] Is very abusive.
[Inaudible].
Thank you.
Next speaker, please next.
I'm here seek liberty and
justice for my domestic partner
a false low imprisoned resident
of loug loug hospital and rehab.
In regards to this endeavour I
have been koren attending
healing commission meetings
after informing the commission
this dt h does not include
laguna honda and rehabs patients
and financial reports.
Healing commission member
colfact announced resignation as
head dph.
Probably just coincident, huh in
also.
Due to delay in finance --
finalizing dph's budget.
Yesterday's planning meeting was
postponed until FEBRUARY 10 with
the full healing commission meet
nothing place of a scheduled
laguna honda hospital and rehab
joint committee conference
meeting on FEBRUARY 10th.
I encourage members of the board
and or the legislative aids to
attend the healing commission
meetingos monday.
That are not holidays.
Thank you.
Thank you for your comments.
>> welcome.
>> hi.
I'm leah I live in d6.
I liked what you said about
unprecedented times.
Calling for unprecedents plan.
Similar to what I think about hi
hear the moderate dem credits
say than I need to be laser
focussed on whatever talking
point and don't present I laze
are focused plan to go with it.
However, I am hearing the plan
at town hall I heard left night
and from the town hall from
other people a lot of details
begin about the mayor and the da
and the board, et cetera, things
they are excited about for the
plan.
Left night I was given this swag
sticker from our da's team.
I'm not going to take it with me
I will leave it there.
Our d acompared hrm reduction
about how you can't get a straw
in star bucks but from the city
to do drugs on the street that
is like a what the f analogy you
want us to get mad they can't
get straws but people suffering
can get straws.
Heartlessness attitude.
I would also like to say I'm
concerned about destableation
stations staffed by police to
walk people up for treatment,
whatever excuse they are giving
for them not behaving.
It was the da said that
condition servitorship takes too
long the people not going to
jail this is a new perktory to
put them in.
Thank you for your comments.
Next speaker, please, welcome.
I'm aaron wilon board of
supervisors the PRESIDENT.
I long with the lady here a
little emotional.
The bayview triage center d 10
with supervisor walton if we can
have your attention as well,
sir.
Why comments to the board as a
whole.
You guys prove over 15 million
dollars to set up the bayview
for r very close's travel
trailers and motor home its is
done and now than I want to
close it down.
I had the electricity come in.
We don't think closing down the
vt c is good we need more places
to put rv's not less.
Now I approached his office.
I sent them do you means and
pictures and letter to the mayor
the shutting down of the vt c.
And as for not an out right term
nigz of the closure, we are
almost there.
In fixing the vt c board of
supervisors.
And we would need I think to
stop it to help of the mayor and
our brierz to get involved
because guess what?
Those rv's are going on the
street.
Youville 30 more vv's.
I think we should reconsider
temperature give it a stay.
Have conversation.
And hopeful low have a change of
heart.
Thank you very much.
>> thank you for your comments.
Good afternoon.
Board of supervisors PRESIDENT,
man, I love it when it rains.
We all share it.
Something we can all agree on
temperature is raining outside.
San francisco is one of the most
beautiful cities in the
westerlied if not the most
beautiful city.
In the world and every day
thousands of tourists from the
world travel to downtown san
francisco union square to begin
their journey tow see the worns
we have to offer here.
And -- unfortunately our
tourists not getting the
experience than I remember from
20005, I was at the battles of
standing rock in 2016.
I spent time in alaska.
I had the honor and privilege to
travel to portugal I seen the
streets are nice and clean.
The women and children are safe.
Tourists come and go as they
please.
I think it is important to
support supervisors moving
forward with firm handled this
is cloning up san francisco.
Love to see the energy we get
for illegalim guarantees if we
get that for the less fortunate
in the streets that will be
great.
Unfortunately there is I
disconnect between citizens.
People are all races and
religions.
we citizen of every color.
When people are going back to
where they came from it must be
bad where they came fro it nice
here I'm live nothing terror
because of the illegal
immigrants.
I have spoke koren
en 32 and throw
introduced without reference to
committee a unanimous vote is
required for adoption of a
resolution on first read today.
A member MAY require a
resolution to go to committee.
Supervisor walton.
>> sever item 33.
>> yes.
I don't see anybody else.
On the balance of the items that
is item 32.
Do we need a roll call.
We don't need a roll call
>> take it 32 same house same
call the resolution is adopted.
And -- call 33.
>> this is I resolution to
recognize and celebrate black
history month in the city and
county of san francisco.
During the month of FEBRUARY
2025.
>> supervisor walton.
>> thank you PRESIDENT Machine
man I want to thank all of you
for your cosponsorship of this
resolution.
As you know every FEBRUARY we
take this time to reflect on
achievements and considerations
and culture and heritage of
black american in our city and
the nation.
I want to acknowledge former
supervisors sophie mechanic
weland doctor brown for
initiating this residence loug
many years ago.
For many of us we celebrate
black history every day.
black history month start in the
then 26 by the doctor carter g.
Woodson founds association for
study of after can american life
and history.
In 1976, PRESIDENT Ford
recognized it during the united
states disen 10 yell and every
PRESIDENT Recognized black
history mont since.
I think up until now.
Today we are witnessing attackod
diversity, equity and he
inclusion as known as the
initiatives across the country.
Effort this is are an attack on
black communities and on
communities of color, queer and
transgender communities
immigrantings people with
disabilities, women and more.
It it is imperative that we
remain critical and fight for
rights our founders fought hard
for.
These roll backs threaten fought
right our ancestors and leaders
fought to dismanual.
We cannot celebrate black
history we must active low
defend and advance it.
That means continuing the fight
for justice, pushing back
against policy thats strip right
and demanding action that
uplifts black communities in san
francisco, that means invest
nothing black communities.
Implementing recommend aces from
reparation plan.
Expanding questions of law
education and supporting black
homeownership and economic
empower am.
As we celebrate black history
among honor the past by shaping
a just and equal future.
One where progress is recognized
and protected and expanded
especially in our currently
times.
With this said I want to
highlight celebrations that we
be having at city hall the next
month.
On friday FEBRUARY 7 at noon,
the african-american cull roll
society will host a black
history month kickoff.
Centered around labor.
Nexted with FEBRUARY 124-seck
P.M. Our d10 office hosting the
black history among art gallery.
And we'll feature art and artist
born and raise in the d 10 who
is on display at the public
library now.
The main library.
And on the evening of wednesday
FEBRUARY 26, will have our huge
black history among celebration
at city hall more details to
follow.
Thank you.
MR. PRESIDENT.
>> thank you, supervisor walton.
I think we can take item 33 same
house same call it is adopted.
MADAM Clerk do we have agenda
items
>> no, MR. PRESIDENT.
Can you read the in memoriams,
in memory of the following
beloved individuals.
Supervisor mandelman for MR.
Richard bollinggroup.
Behalf of supervisor we have for
MR. Allen baird.
My apologies supervisor
mandelman.
>> thank you.
MADAM Clerk that brings us to
the en of our agenda.
Is there further business today?
That concludes our business.